Okay, and in this last session of the
afternoon today
we return to computer systems and
I think we return to
computer systems in the best way that we
can return to computer systems today
, which is by exploring how
what we just did in the
intermodular project is then applied within
computer systems,
that is, In the first part of
computer systems today we
created a server, a to server.  But
why did we create it?  Well,
we created it for precisely these
things.  We created it to then
launch an application into production.
These little apps that I'm
creating in class today, okay?
full stack refresh, which is what we
did today in the intermodular project.  These are
applications that I'm
running on my machine, okay?  On my
specific machine, on my
particular machine, in development, what for
you will be Windows.  But there comes a
time when this has to be moved into
production.
Moving software into production is
an art, and now in
the first quarter we'll be evaluating it
in a small way, and obviously,
as the course progresses, we'll be
doing it more extensively.
So, today we are going to work on the
simplest way.  Later on,
especially in the second quarter,
I'll show you how to push to production
using git, okay?  and using
yub, but that is more complex.  So
now what I want is the following.
Let's go to, let's see, let's go to
computer systems,
let's go to 002,
preparatory exercise, exam,
and we're going to create a new file called
008, go to production.
Okay?  In a production move, we want to
move the code,
the intermodular project
from the
development environment
to the production environment.
What have we used today?
What have we used?  Well, we've used
Python plus Flask
and that's it.  Okay, we haven't done anything
else but that little ass, sorry.  The question is, does
our environment
have those tools?
The answer
is yes.  Because?  Well, because a
little while ago, a little
while ago we installed Flask.
And that little ass 3 doesn't need to be installed
because it's already installed.
Okay, now how do we connect
the development environment to the
production environment?
Simpler answer,
little file.
Our
uh our server
already has Open SSH server.
In our development environment
we installed filecilla.
Filecilla client.
No, no, nothing against SCP.
SCP is initially more oriented
towards the Windows world, that is, to
connect to a Windows Server,
while in the Linux world SSH is used
more, but not in any way against
SCP.  In fact, when I've needed to and I've been
and I've been on Windows, I've used
Win SCP, which is a program that in the
end is very intuitive, it's the
left side of your computer, the right side
of the server, you drag from one side
to the other if you want to go up or
down.  So no, nothing against SCP
at all.  Okay?  So now I come
here and make sure that
the filecilla client is installed on my computer
.  Okay, so yes, exactly,
correct.  Okay, so it works
great and in the end it's very
similar in the sense that look,
notice that FCILA has a left part and a
right part and I go to these
and I go to win SCP.  I'm looking for a screenshot,
okay?  I go to Windows CP and if you
look,
if I put a screenshot of Win SCP and put
file Cila, well it looks the same, okay?
It's simply your computer on the left,
the remote server on the right, so in the
end the concept is the same.  So I
come over here and now what I'm going to
do is I'm going to set up a new Exactly,
correct.  I set up a new connection,
okay?  We configure a new connection and
for that a new site and I say
SFTP protocol, okay?  And that's why the CILA file is
already prepared.
SFTP SSH protocol.
Now server,
well do you remember 192 168
151.
User
José Vicente was in my case and password
give me a 23.
Okay, so okayok.  Okay.
Okay.  Server 192, 168, 1151.
User José Vicente.  Password, tame 1
2 3
and we connect.
We connect.  We accept password.
And here, as you can see, on the
right side the server has loaded.
So,
once connected,
on the left side,
your local development team
, on the right side,
your remote production team.  Remote
means that today it is a
virtual machine, so it is not so
remote, it is on our machine, that is, it
is on our own computer, but
we are simulating that it is a
remote production server.
Therefore,
drag
from left
to right to
upload files to the server
from right to left.
Download files
from the server.
Right now it tells us that we are in the
root folder Home José Vicente.  Okay, I
like it, I like being there.
Next I'm going to create
a new directory called, for
example, production pass,
for example, whatever name you want, okay?   I
create a new directory, go to production,
go to the new directory and now
from the local environment, from the
development environment, I'm going to transfer files
to the remote server.  Leave.  In my
case they are in bar, they are in HTMW,
in HTML, in Dam, a little while
in Dam
25 26
or first
intermodular project,
eh, exercises, refresh full stack,
exercises and here, okay, I move everything
up.
Okay.  Okay, so as you can see, what I've done
is drag from the left to the
right and that makes sure I've
just copied the files into
production.
Now next, now
next I come over here and say,
"Okay, now
file new 009
start service dot python
and then I come over here and for example
I say, let's see
where you are. I
stop clear. No, this is my own
computer outside.
This is the server. Yes, LS. Okay, you see
that when doing an LS I have a
production pass.
Wait. Clear LS. Production pass.
I am, I insist on Ubuntu Server José
Vicente, okay? Uh, CD Production pass
LS and I have here uh the files that I
had on my computer.
Let's let's
see.
011 20 products better I separate it into three
blocks. I'm going to say Python 3 008. It
stopped in three blocks and tells us, this
is the problem and it tells us, "Okay, I'm
listening on port 5000,
but I'm listening on IP 127001.
First problem in going to production,
well what happened is that the IP where I
'm listening now
is technically not  127001,
but it's eh well this one, right?  Let's see
the IP for a moment.  Just a moment, just a
moment,
IP 192 168 151.
So, so, I'll stop and of course,
now I can do one of two things or what
I can do now is force an IP or
tell it to listen on all
interfaces.  Okay, I'm going to say sweat
nano 01, no, 00, I don't remember,
wait.  008.
I edit the file.
Oh, sorry.  this,
okay?  And I go down
and in the application run
in parameters I'm going to say host is
equal to 0.0.0.0 in
quotes.
0.0.0.0
runs on all IPs.
Run, listen on all
interfaces.  I hit control o, control
X and run again.  And now it tells me And
now it tells me, "I'm listening to you on
interface 127001,
but I'm also listening to you on
interface 192 168 1 151,
which means that now I'm
coming over here somewhere,
here I come over here, I'm going to close
tabs, I
come over here. and I say 192 168 151
port 8000
sorry 5000 not 8000
and as you can see what's happening is
that I have the products
loaded but from the server. I just
did a deploy to the server and I'm
running the application from the
server itself. I
can do the same thing, for example, with
what I did in the last exercise.
I'm going to stop the server for a moment.
LS. The last project was 016,
several pages and several templates. Well,
nano 016 sweated.
I go all the way down
and I say host is equal to 0.0.0.0.
Okay, yeah. Just a moment, yeah  Edit.
Sure. Just a moment, just a moment. Good
question, Piero. Let's go. Let's
see. Now I run Python nano.
Python 3
nano Python 3
and then now
I reload and this is José Vicente's website
, home page about me and
contact. Okay,
good. Let's see. Piero, that's a very
good question that gives me the opportunity to
explain something very important to you. Right
now, what
we're doing is working on the first
trimester of the first year and what
I want is for things
to work first and second, and this is almost more
important, for them to be easy
for you to understand. But there are times when
doing that we incur, not
intentionally, but for the sake of
clarity, in practices that cannot be
considered good practices for a
very simple reason.
I have
a production environment, a development environment,
that is, I have a development environment
and I transfer this to a production environment,
but of course,
now
here I make modifications,
but be careful
now Here I might make other
modifications.
I know that this is going to lead me to a
train wreck. Because if I
commit  To make all the
modifications in the
development environment, I know that every time I make
a modification in development, I upload it to
production and that's it.
If I make the modifications, it
's also possible directly in the
development environment, because I know that every x amount of time
I make a copy in the local environment and that
's it, a backup.
But if I make some modifications
in the development environment and other
modifications in the
production environment, in the end that's going to clash
because in the end if I upload this, I'll
ruin the modifications I've
made in production. And if I
download this to my computer, I'll ruin the
modifications I've made in the
development environment. Okay? What's
happening? Right now, this doesn't
matter to me. I'm aware, obviously,
that this isn't just something that can
happen, but that it actually happens.
But I'm not worried about it right now,
because what worries me is doing this
in a simple way and for you to
understand it. And once you've
understood it, then from there, we
'll evolve and grow in the following quarters
. Let's see.  Just a
moment here. Okay, I have someone,
wait,
who left the microphone
on. Sorry.
Oh, okay. Okay, I was going to check the
microphones. So, I'm telling you now that,
well, it's not Piero who's bad anymore, okay?
It's not a question of good or bad, but rather
, as I always say, of pros and
cons, of advantages and disadvantages. But it
's too early to start talking to you about
advantages and disadvantages. Right now, the
only thing I'm worried about is that you all
understand it, that it works for all of you, that you
start to notice, that you start to feel
that you have control over this, and
once you feel that, in the second
trimester, we'll start talking about good
practices, how to do it right, how to
do it cleanly, and all that, okay? In
fact, you'll see that many of the things I
'm teaching you, well, in the
second and third trimesters,
I'll tell you, "Okay, I've taught you a little bit
in a, let's say,
dirty way.  And now we're going to do it clean.
But now the goal, as I say, is
for you to learn it, to get excited, to
say, "Okay, this is starting to make
sense."  that you see this diagram from
before, well, this diagram here and
say, "Okay, I'm starting to understand the
system, I'm starting to understand the diagram,
that you come this way,
that you come this way
and say, okay, I understand that
development environments is something that encompasses this and I
understand
and I understand that computer systems
is something that encompasses all of this here and
with this we already have the complete pack of
subjects and integration of what
each subject is for, okay? And and well,
and I'm going to, I think that more or less I'll
end today's sessions by
saying one thing, now I'm going to talk
a little about programming and I'm going to refresh
a concept that I probably
explained at the beginning of the course, but
that it's probably also good to
refresh now. Look.
In the learning of
programming,
this graph is usually drawn that I'm going
to draw for you.
This graph
represents,
let's paint a couple of arrows.
Let's look at
this page. This page, this graph.
represents
the effort
versus the result.
The problem is that
let's see
if this is the same  Drawing
backwards. Let's see it.
The problem is that the graph
is like this.
There's
stroke color. There's no fill.
And no. And here
there.
And this here,
this is the
computer science learning graph,
which effectively means it's
wrong, it's upside down.
Okay, this is effort
and this is result.
And this graph is saying that at the
beginning,
at the beginning
we're going to lower the transparency.
At the beginning, you apply a lot of effort,
a lot of effort for little
result.
And that's what I'm trying to change in the
intermodular project course,
apart from the fact that we have to deal with
market research,
competition analysis and all that, and
current legislation and all that, which we also have to
do, but above all my
goal is to mix technologies
so that this bitter moment I'm
putting on the screen passes as soon as
possible, because this is where many
people stop.
Okay, this is where many people stop
and this is where many people drop out.
Because the moment you say,
"Look, I apply four times more effort
than result, this programming thing isn't
worth it."  This programming thing is more difficult
than anything else.  If you wait a little
longer,
if you wait a little longer
and if you have a little patience, it
turns out
that as you move forward,
we're going to paint it a different color.
If you apply twice the effort, you
get three times the result.
That means that as time goes by, it
starts to pay off more.
Because?  And I think you can already
begin to see this.  Because it supports you
on what you already know.  It's not about learning
new things every day, but rather,
from a certain point, it's about using the
things you already know to build on
them and go further.
What's going on?  That if you have a little
patience
and wait a little longer,
then it turns out
that there comes a point
where by applying a little more
effort you get a lot of
results.
And if you wait a little longer
and have enough patience,
with a little more effort, you
get a lot more results.
Okay?  So,
so that's why my goal, okay,
is here at the beginning.  This is the dangerous point
and it's the point where, you know, you
are right now, okay?
The goal is not just to make
programming fun, because
you'll never hear me say, especially at the
beginning, that programming is
fun.  Then it is, right?
Then when you already know a lot about
programming it does become
quite fun, but at first it
isn't, honestly it isn't.
Programming is useful.  Programming
allows you to build
computer tools, and
computer tools are useful to
people, right?  Both on a
professional and personal level.  That is to
say, what you learn with
programming, I insist, is useful, but
I can't say that it's fun and
certainly much less can I say that it's
easy.   That's why
my goal at the beginning of this
course, as I said, is: I'm
aware of this curve, I want
you to be aware of this curve,
and that's why right now what I want is to
try to do exercises that
communicate to you in the simplest way
possible what's coming up,
what's going to happen next, what
we can expect in the coming
quarters, okay?  And that's it.  That's
why a lot of the things I
'm doing in class are, as
I would say, things I'm doing in a
dirty way,
like mixing Python and HTML, to give
a concrete example of what I'm
telling you,
but I don't care about that right now.  I
mean, I'm aware of that, I'm
perfectly aware of it in the
Python and HTML example and a lot of other
things, but I don't care, okay?  No, I don't
want to teach you purism, I want
you to, as far as possible, have fun within
the non-fun inherent in
programming, okay?
And that's all there is to it.  So that's
all for today, but
wait a second, a second, a
second, don't leave because we had
this pending, which is to
send you the email regarding the
exams.
So,
uh, okay, development environments, what are
you going to need?  Hey, let's see for a
moment.  Development lathes,
same
tools
as in languages ​​and programming.
Intermodular project.
Eh, let's see, the same tools
as in programming
brands and computer systems,
Mysqulamp and Python programming.  Okay,
Python plus GDP.  Very good.  Exams.
Let's see.  Computer systems.   The
essence
of the exam,
okay?  Essence of the exam.
Essence of the exam.
Essence of the exam
and essence of the exam.
Okay, so I'm going to take advantage and
send it to you now because otherwise I'll
forget about it later.
Okay, then
let's go.
Okay.
Uh,
first evaluation exams.
Give me one.  Okay.
Okay.  Exams.
Hello everyone.   I am
informing you of
the dates and times scheduled for the
first evaluation exams.
This is here.
Okay.
The computer
will be empty and Windows will need to be
installed
on the day of the exam.
You can come a little earlier.
Samp exam.
Okay, the exams
are in person
at the
TAME facilities.
Okay.
Summary
of the essence of the exams.   Please
refer to the classes or
class recordings for
more precise instructions and drills.
Okay, this is for me.  No, this is not it.
Okay, this is for me.
for Amparo, for
David, for Javier,
okay?  And for you, of course.
So
I'm coming this way, I'm
coming this way.
Wait a minute.
Okay, okay.
Ah, I'm going to take advantage of this to put.
Remember that exams
are worth 50% of the
quarterly evaluation.
20%
are ongoing activities,
subunits,
20% are
end-of-unit activities, and 10% is the
extra mile.
Okay?
So, I'm sending this to you.
Okay.
And to Ramón.  And to Ramón.
Okay,
then sent.
Okay, now we continue on Thursday and
practice all that.  Yes, the
extra mile thing is what I told you about in
an email recently, I think.  10% of the grade
is a project that you do.  What does
this mean?  I'll fill you with
activities, okay?  I tell you, you have to
do this, you have to do this
activity, you have to do this
exercise, you have to do, I mean, I
tell you, you have, you have, you have, you have,
okay?  I don't leave you, I don't leave you freedom.
That 10%
is 10% of freedom.  It is a 10% in
which each of you at the end of
each term, in each subject,
have to do a project that is
free, a project that I have not told you
what you have to do, but you
taking the contents of that
subject have to create a project,
whichever you want.  I mean, for
example, let's give some
concrete examples, uh, markup languages,
okay?  Exactly, Piero, indeed, that is
a good description.  It is
mandatory, but the theme is free.
Well, sorry, it's mandatory, I
mean, it's 10% of the grade, okay?  But it
is mandatory, let's say, it is
qualifiable, it is scored.  So,
markup language, for example, I
tell you to make a series of
web pages,
but the extra mile is that you make a
web page of whatever you want, I have
n't told you what you want, what it
is, but you have chosen it and
in that project you apply the
knowledge of markup language and you
show me that you have understood
markup language.  programming.
We do a series of projects in class.
I give you activities, I tell you what you have to
do, but going the
extra mile, you make a
computer application with Python that does something
you want to do, but I didn't
tell you, you chose it, okay?
So, the extra mile is for you to go
further, to start with 10% to go
beyond what I tell you,
using the knowledge I've
taught you, of course, but to take
a project of your own choice, okay?  Of
free choice of theme.  As
the quarters progress,
free projects will have more importance
in the evaluation and
guided activities will have less importance.  But
now that we're starting, obviously
most of the assessment is
guided exercises where I say,
you have to do this and this and this and a
little bit of freedom and as we
progress through the course, there will be more
freedom, okay?  That's the extra mile.
So, that's it, see you on Thursday.
We continue on Thursday with
markup languages, databases, and programming.   On
Thursday, we'll be working
on mock exams and
preparing for the exam, just like
today.  And nothing, and that's it.  Okay, if
anything goes, we'll talk in the group and nothing,
see you guys until Thursday.